<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from Moses Pitt, to the authour of a book, intituled, some discourses upon Dr. Burnet, now Ld. Bp. of Salisbury and Dr. Tillotson, late Ld. A.B. of Canterbury occasioned by the late funeral sermon of the former upon the latter.</title>
            <author>Pitt, Moses, fl. 1654-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7270</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11799550</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11799550</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 545:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from Moses Pitt, to the authour of a book, intituled, some discourses upon Dr. Burnet, now Ld. Bp. of Salisbury and Dr. Tillotson, late Ld. A.B. of Canterbury occasioned by the late funeral sermon of the former upon the latter.</title>
                  <author>Pitt, Moses, fl. 1654-1696.</author>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
                  <author>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pitt was writing to George Hickes. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715. --  Sermon preached at the funeral of ... John ... Lord Archbishop of Canterbury.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49355:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM Moſes Pitt, TO THE AUTHOUR of a Book, INTITULED, <hi>Some Diſcourſes upon D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               </hi> Burnet (<hi>now L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p.</hi> of</hi> Salisbury) <hi>and D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               </hi> Tillot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (<hi>late L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> A.B. of</hi> Canterbury;) Occaſioned by the Late <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> of the former upon the latter.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deuteronomy, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. <hi>V.</hi> 16, 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl> If a falſe Witneſs riſe up againſt a Man to teſtifie againſt him, that which is wrong:</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Then both the Men between whom the Controverſie is ſhall ſtand before the Lord, before the Prieſts, and the Judges, which ſhall be in thoſe Days.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49355:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49355:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER from <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> To the Authour of a Book, Intituled, <hi>Some Diſcourſes upon Dr.</hi> Burnet <hi>and Dr.</hi> Tillotſon; <hi>occaſioned by the late</hi> Funeral-Sermon <hi>of the former on the latter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LAtely walking the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> a Citizen of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance calls me into his Shop, and tells me that he was glad to ſee me, and that he deſired me to tell him the Truth of what he ſhould ask me, I told him I would as near as I could; upon that he proceeds in his Diſcourſe, and ſaid, that he had ſeen a Book lately come forth againſt Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> the now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury;</hi> which, ſaith he, if the things are true therein related of him, he is a very ill Man (or Words to that effect) and you are quoted to juſtifie one of the Paſſages mentioned in the ſaid Book about Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Book to Duke <hi>Lauderdale:</hi> I replied I could not anſwer him till I ſaw the Book and paſſage there in mentioned, wherein I was quored for Authority; upon which I made it my buſineſs to get one of your Books, which with much difficulty I did, and in Reading of it, in Page the <hi>18th.</hi> and <hi>19th.</hi> I found this Paſſage in relation to the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Sabisbury</hi> (which I have here ſet down <hi>Verbatim,</hi> by reaſon your Book is not eaſily by every Reader to be got) which is as followeth. <q>I ſhall now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to things of ſomething of a different Nature; but which will ſhew no leſs what little Credit to be given to him, and how unſafe it is to rely upon his Authority. He dedicated his <hi>Vindication of the Authority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Laws of</hi> Scotland, to the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> then High Commiſſioner of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> In that Dedication he tells the Duke, <hi>How worthily he bore that noble Character, with the more laſting and noble Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49355:3"/>of a Princely mind, and praiſes him for the long uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Tranquility that Kingdom had enjoyed under his wiſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Conduct;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>That he was a Prince greater in his Mind than Fortune, and that there was ſomething inward to him, which commanded all the Reſpect that could be paid by all ſuch that had the Honour to know him, as well as he did.</hi> He acknowledges alſo the <hi>particular</hi> Engagement <hi>by which he was obliged to him;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>That it was not fit for him to expreſs the Senſe he had of them, and of the vaſt Endowments of his Mind, for fear he ſhould ſeem to flatter him.</hi> Then he inſtances in the <hi>profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Underſtanding, and well-ballanced Judgment; for which he might deſervedly paſs for a Maſter in all Learning.</hi> And, in the Concluſion tells him, <hi>That from him they expected an happy Settlement, and wiſhed that Succeſs Bleſſings might attend his Endeavours.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Not long after the printing of this Book at <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> he brought a great Part of the Impreſſion to <hi>London,</hi> where he ſold it to Mr. <hi>Moſes Pitt;</hi> and not long after that again, he came to him to deſire him with great Earneſtneſs to ſell the Copies of it without the Dedication: (For by this time the Duke had fallen out with him, and diſcarded him for ſome Arts and Qualities he had obſerved in him, which I need not name.) Mr. <hi>Pitt</hi> gave him very good Reaſons why he ought not to do ſo; and particularly told him, he could not honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſell an imperfect for a perfect Copy: Upon which he was angry, and threatened him with the loſs of all the Favours he intended to do him in his Trade. This Mr. <hi>Pitt</hi> can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, if he is living; but if he is not, it can be atteſted by an honourable Perſon, who heard him ſolicite Mr. <hi>Pitt</hi> to this baſe unworthy Practice. But though Mr. <hi>Pitt</hi> would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſell the Book without the Dedication, yet he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to let him have them again, and then they came abroad without it. And ſo hard it was till it was privately Reprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to get one ſingle Copy with it, that I profeſs I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver get ſuch a one, till a Gentleman preſented me with one out of his private Study. And when he delated his Patron to the Houſe of Commons, Sir <hi>A. Forreſter,</hi> his Grace's Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, told me, That after the utmoſt diligence he could get but one ſingle Copy with the Dedication, though he would have purchaſed more at any Rate, to ſhew the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49355:3"/>of the honourable Houſe what kind of Man his <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencer</hi> was, that would publiſh ſuch things in the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Duke, after he knew<note n="(a)" place="margin">See his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication in his <hi>xvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>j</hi> Papers.</note> as he pretended, <hi>he had a Deſign of bringing in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my out of</hi> Scotland, <hi>for the ſpoiling and ſubduing of</hi> England.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This diſcovery of the Dedication, and his ſuppreſſing of it coming to be known, made all the Houſe curious to ſee it, and he foreſeeing what uſe would be made of it againſt him, was willing to decline his noble Undertaking. But the Houſe, by the Intereſt of the Duke's Friends, who increaſed much upon that Diſcovery, made him reſtifie what he ſince ſaith, <hi>created Horrour</hi> in him; and how much Reputation he got by it I need not now tell the World; I am ſure many of the Duke's grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Enemies looked upon it as an horrible Lye; not thinking the Deſign, or the Diſcovery of it, if he had deſigned it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſo much Wiſdom as he was Maſter of, above moſt great Men of his Time.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sir, after I had read, not only this Paſſage, but, the whole Book over, I conſider'd with my ſelf what Perſon or Perſons were alive at that time when I printed for Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (for its now above 20 Years paſt) that could any ways help my Memory, that ſo I might declare to you and the World <hi>the Truth, the whole Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth,</hi> in this Matter or Paſſage you call me, if living, to teſtiſie. Sir, you muſt know that I am of the <hi>Cobler</hi>'s Mind, that lived in <hi>Holborn</hi> in King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>1ſt</hi>'s Time, when <hi>Goundemore</hi> the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> was paſſing by in his Chair, the Sedan-men happening to ſtumble, and fall, and the <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> being on the Ground, Multitudes of People came running at this Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, one of which cries to the <hi>Cobler</hi> to come out of his Stall and help up the <hi>Ambaſſadour;</hi> The <hi>Cobler</hi> replies, not he, for he would not meddle with State-matters. But conſidering with my ſelf that two mighty Things are concerned in this Paſſage of yours, that is, <hi>Truth,</hi> and a <hi>Good-name;</hi> the latter of which <hi>Solc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tells us, <hi>is better than precious Ointment:</hi> And for the former, <hi>Truth,</hi> it's an Attribute of our great and good <hi>God,</hi> and it's the Duty of all Men to imitate <hi>God</hi> in this Attribute, and That Man is worſe than the Beaſts that periſhed that is not a Man of <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> makes a Man as bold as a <hi>Lion:</hi> Ask the <hi>Lawyers</hi> what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49355:4"/>plead for they will tell you for <hi>Truth:</hi> Ask the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of all perſwaſions what they preach, and they will tell you <hi>Truth:</hi> Ask all <hi>Writers</hi> of <hi>Books</hi> in all Arts and Sciences what they have written, and they will tell you <hi>Truth.</hi> You your ſelf ſay in this your Book, ſpeaking againſt Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> 
               <q>You ſay, you could produce more Inſtances out of <hi>Beedle</hi>'s Life, to ſhew how apt he was to write his own Inventions for true Hiſtory, and thereby impoſe upon the World, and you believe you have brought enough for that purpoſe, and hope you have thereby convinced all Lovers of <hi>Truth,</hi> more than of Men's Perſons, how unſaſe it is to take things upon Truſt from him (<hi>page</hi> 33) and Sir,</q> I find you your felf ſo much a Lover of <hi>Truth</hi> (as you pretend at leaſt) that I hope you will not be angry with me for declaring the <hi>Truth;</hi> in this Paſſage you your ſelf appeal to me in, between the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the now Lord. Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>18th.</hi> and <hi>19th.</hi> Pages of your ſaid <hi>Bock.</hi> And Sir, I ſhall ſpeak the <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo as you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to expreſs it in the <hi>1ſt.</hi> and <hi>2d.</hi> Pages of your Preſace to your ſaid Book. So as it may <hi>ſerve to inform and entertain inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Searchers after Truth.</hi> And then you go on and ſay, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Dr. <hi>Jo. Tillot ſon,</hi> late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Againſt whom</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you have been provoked to draw up two ſeveral Charges or Informations which ſomewhat blomiſh their Honour; ſo you hope you have proved them in every part by very good Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And as ſome Trials are longer than others, according to the Number and Length of Depoſitions; ſo if this Book of mine which contains as it were ſo many Depoſitions againſt them, hath proved longer than I would have had it, that is none of my Fault.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And you farther ſay; <q>you know very well it will be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Libel, and a Defamatory Libel, but you care not for that; ſince many excellent Books were ſo miſcalled in the Times of our former Uſurpations, which detected the ill Men of thoſe Times, and their Hypocriſies, and Imquities to the World.</q> The ſame thing have I done lately in a Book called, <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed,</hi> printed 1691. Wherein I have detected many Men by Name now hving (ſome of them in great ſplendor) of <hi>Oppreſſion, Extortion, Bribery, Perjury, Bluſphemy,</hi> and ſeveral other the like Crimes, and there has not to this Day, <hi>Nav.</hi> 1695. any one of the Paſſages therein mentioned been contradicted,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49355:4"/>and I ſtill challenge any one therein accuſed to clear himſelf from thoſe Villanies I therein charge him with, for I am ſtill ready to prove on them all the Matters of Fact I have therein related, (thus hold is Truth.) And then you go on and ſay (and I agree with you, and ſo I believe will all good Men.) <q>And beſides, to ſpeak properly and juſtly of the Nature of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, all Books onght not to be ſo called, which expoſe Men's Reputations; but ſuch only as expoſe them falſly, injuriouſly, and out of pure Malice: But this Book, though in ſome things it blemiſhes the Fame and Reputation of theſe Men, yet it doth it truly, juſtly, and deſervedly; and ſo far am I from bearing the Perſon of the one, or the Memory of the other any Malice; that had I been acted by that evil Paſſion, I could have written againſt them both much ſooner, and have been better provided to write againſt them now. Men that do ill things openly, and with an high hand, though under never ſo ſplendid Pretences, ought to hear of them; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they go about to make Saints and Heroes of one another, with a Deſign to cover their own Iniquities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the People. When this happens to be the Caſe, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the People's Souls, and the Love of the Publick, obliges all Lovers of Truth and Righteouſneſs to unvizard ſuch Men, and expoſe them in their true Appearance before their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous and deluded Admirers.</q> (As to this laſt Paragraph ſo far all good Men will agree with you, but how far the World will believe you as to theſe two popular Divines (as you are pleaſed to call them) when I have told my Matters or given my Depoſition, as you your ſelf are pleaſed to term it, I leave it to judgment.) <q>And as I have endeavoured in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſes to do ſo, by theſe two popular Divines; ſo I aſſure the Reader I have done it purely upon theſe generous Motives, wiſhing with all my Heart, that neither of them had given ſo many and publick Provocations to undeceive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the World by writing ſuch ſevere Truths. So much I have taken out of your own Preface,</q> and now Sir, I will go on and give you the <hi>Truth</hi> of this Matter you mention in Page the <hi>18th.</hi> and <hi>19th.</hi> of your Book, as touching that Paſſage of the Dedication of Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet's Vindication of the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Laws of</hi> Scotland, to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> as far as I know or can any way call to my Remembrance. And this I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49355:5"/>do as in the Preſence of the Great <hi>God,</hi> who is the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the True <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Angels,</hi> and of <hi>Men;</hi> and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Reſpect to the Perſon of the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> with whom I have had no Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neither by word of mouth not by writing, or otherwiſe, ſince he leſt <hi>England</hi> in King <hi>James</hi>'s Days, otherwiſe than that very ſoon after I printed my <hi>Cry of the Oppreſſed</hi> which was in 1691, or before, I believe I might ſend him as I did ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Biſhops and Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Letter with one of my ſaid Books, but I never received any Anſwer from him, neither directly nor indirectly (only Mr. <hi>Richard Chiſwel</hi> the laſt Time but one that I ſaw him, told me, that the Biſhop ask'd him how I did, and that he was ſorry for my Misfortunes; but whether Mr. <hi>Chiſwell</hi> did this in a Complement I know not, neither did it affect me) neither doth the <hi>Biſhop</hi> know of what I now write, neither have I, or any Perſon for me, any way applied my ſelf to him about this or any other Matter, (although very much urged to it by ſome of my Friends) ſince he came into <hi>England</hi> with King <hi>William.</hi> Neither has he, the ſaid Biſhop, applied himſelf to me, neither by himſelf or any Friend that I know of to declare my Knowledge in this Matter, neither is it any Envy, Spleen or Malice I have to your Perſon, for you treat me very civilly, and have repreſented me an honeſt Man in tranſacting the Affair between the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and my <hi>Self,</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your Story had been <hi>True,</hi> and further I ſay, if <hi>Truth</hi> had been on your Side, I would have declared it to the World as freely, and as willingly as I now do. And this I have now here ſaid has been againſt the Intreaties of ſome of my neareſt and deareſt Relations, they uſing their Arguments to me that I ſhould diſoblige a great Number of my Friends; ſome of them of the firſt Rank of Great Men, and that you had not treated me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, but have ſpoken well of me, and had not diſobliged me; and therefore what need had I to be ſo much concerned, as to declare the <hi>Truth</hi> in this matter, (or Arguments to this effect?) To which I replied, and that with ſome Zeal, That if both their Lives and my own alſo lay at ſtake with <hi>Truth,</hi> and that either our Lives or <hi>Truth.</hi> muſt be parted with, we muſt part with our Lives and keep to <hi>Truth.</hi> Further, I told them, I was by you called on to ſpeak the <hi>Truth</hi> in this matter; your Words are, <hi>This Mr.</hi> Pitt <hi>can teſtifie if he is living:</hi> By this I have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49355:5"/>wrote, you may ſee I am living for to tell you and the World the <hi>Truth</hi> of this Matter of Fact, to the beſt of my Knowledge and Remembrance, it being above 20 Years ſince that this Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Duke <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the preſent Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> happened. Now to the Paſſage it ſelf.</p>
            <p>After, Sir, I had read your Book, I conſidered who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live at that Time, when this Affair you call me to witneſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that could any way help my Memory, and there accrued to my Memory, one Mr. <hi>Adam Angus,</hi> at this preſent Time, Reader at St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> in the Weſt, <hi>London,</hi> who was about the Year 1675. as he told me, Amanuenſis to Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> whom I found out, and I diſcourſed him about this Matter at ſeveral Times; at the ſecond Meeting with him, I ſhewed him Dr. <hi>Burnet's Vindication of the Authority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Laws of Scotland,</hi> in which was the Dedication to Duke <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> and your ſaid Book, and deſired him to read the <hi>18th.</hi> and <hi>19th.</hi> Pages, which he did with ſome Conſideration, and at all the Meetings he gave me this ſincere Account, and was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſurprized at ſuch groundleſs Expreſſions (this was on or about the ſecond Day of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1695. and the other Meetings was about a Day, or few Days before or after.) That as for the Book it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Burnet's Vindication,</hi> &amp;c. he did believe that it was ſent me by the Bookſeller that printed it, or ſome other Bookſeller out of <hi>Scotland;</hi> there being more printed there than could vend in that Kingdom, and that I was to give Books in way of Barter for them, and that I had them not from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour: then I ask'd him if either the Doctour, or he had any of the ſaid Books from me, he anſwered me that they had not, to the beſt of his Remembrance, but ſaid, that that <hi>Dedication</hi> to Duke <hi>Lauderdale</hi> had made a great noiſe in the World; then I ask'd him if he did remember that any of the books were ſold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Dedication,</hi> he told me, he did not remember that any was, (neither do I remember there was, or that ever Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> had any of them of me, either with or without, the <hi>Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>) Then I ask'd him whether Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> did deſire me with earneſtneſs to ſell the Copies of it without the <hi>Dedication,</hi> and whether he was angry with me, and threatned me with the Loſs of all the Favours he intended to do me in my Trade; he anſwered me <hi>Fy, Fy,</hi> there was no ſuch thing ſaid or done, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, I remembred no ſuch thing or expreſſion; for it might be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49355:6"/>ſuppoſed, if there had, it was ſo harſh a one, that no Man in way of Trade, as I was, could forget it all Days of his Life: I alſo ask'd him if he remembred what Books I printed of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s, he anſwered me, I printed his <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd</hi> (this was a Book he printed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and by his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I reprinted it here in <hi>London,</hi> in 1673. which was the Year his <hi>Vindication of the Authority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Laws of Scotland</hi> was printed at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> by <hi>Robert Sanders,</hi> and this was before Mr. <hi>Adam Angus</hi> was Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Amanuenſis) then he told me I printed Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> and Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi>'s (now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>) Conference with Mr. <hi>Edward Coleman</hi> (this was the <hi>Coleman</hi> whom Dr. <hi>Titus Oates</hi> cauſed afterward to be ſeized, and alſo his Letters which ſo fully diſcovered the Popiſh Plot, for which he was hanged, <hi>December</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> 1678. although he was then Secretary, or reputed Secretary to the then Dutcheſs of <hi>York</hi>) an others of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which Conference Mr. <hi>Adam Angus</hi> told me, he took in Writings from Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet</hi>'s own Mouth, after it was over, which he ſhewed to Dr. <hi>Edward Stillingfleet,</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Edward Coleman,</hi> &amp;c. who all of them owned it under their Hands that it was faithfully taken; this Book being brought me in M. S. by Mr. <hi>Adam Angus,</hi> I printed it in the Year 1676. and it made 17 Sheets of Paper, for which I gave Mr. <hi>Adam Angus</hi> 17 <hi>l.</hi> I further ask'd Mr. <hi>Adam Angus</hi> if Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> had the Moneys or any part of it, he told me very frankly and readily, no, not one Farthing, for he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> owned he had it for his own uſe for his Care about it. Then he farther ſaid, I printed Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> this was a Pamphlet (what you accuſe the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> about it in the 23 <hi>d.</hi> Page of your Book, is his own Province to anſwer, for; I am altogether a Stranger to that Paſſage; all I ſay, I believe Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> brought it me, and I printed it as the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s Book.) Then Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> told me, he thought I printed another Book of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> but he could not well call it to mind, neither can I. Then I ask'd how it came to paſs that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> forſook me, and gave his Copies to another Bookſeller, in anſwer to which, he gave me the following Account. That I was to give him the ſaid Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> 10 <hi>l.</hi> more, if I printed another Impreſſion, and that the Printer, who was <hi>Henry Critenden,</hi> ſince dead, had told him I had ſo done, for which Reaſon he thought fit to employ
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49355:6"/>another, and tranſacted with him, and that the Doctour was innocent and knew nothing of this Tranſaction till afterwards: I replied, I had not printed a ſecond Edition of the ſaid Book, but I did believe, that by the Perſuaſion of the Printer, I did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him to print a greater Number of the latter Sheets, than of the Firſt, out of hopes that it would have come to a ſecond Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and thereby I ſhould have ſaved the Charges of compoſing ſo many of the laſt Sheets, but I was diſappointed in my Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, and ſo I was forced to make waſt Paper of all them ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumerary Sheets. So by this miſunderſtanding between Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> and my <hi>Self,</hi> I loſt my Authour the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> for which I cannot in the leaſt blame Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> (as you call him) what I have here wrote, as far as Mr. <hi>Adam Angus</hi> is concerned in this Paragraph is <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I have done what I can to refreſh my Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I will own what is <hi>Truth,</hi> and diſown what is not, ſo far as you appeal to me in your Book, <hi>page</hi> 18 and 19. for, I find, you lay a great ſtreſs on this Book of Dr. <hi>Burnet's Vindication of the Authority, Conſtitution and Laws of Scotland.</hi> For except <hi>Terent. in Prolog. ante Eunuchum;</hi> it's the only Authour or Book you quote in the very Title Page of your Diſcourſes, and you quote Page the <hi>4th.</hi> of the <hi>Doctour</hi>'s ſaid Book; the Words are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; <q>Remember how ſeverely he that was Meekneſs it ſelf, treated the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> and he having charged his Followers to beware of their Leaven, it is obedience to his Command to ſearch out that Leaven, that it may leaven us no more. And when any of a Party are ſo exalted in their own Conceit, as to deſpiſe and diſparage all others, the <hi>Love</hi> the Miniſters of the Goſpel owe the Souls of their Flocks, obligeth them to <hi>Unmask</hi> them.</q> Sir, this Quotation of yours is <hi>True;</hi> for, I have compared it; only you have a <hi>The</hi> between <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> more than is in the Doctour's Book, but that's not material; the Reaſon why I am ſo critical is, becauſe I write as if I made an Affidavit before a Maſter in Chancery: For <hi>Livy</hi> the Famous Roman Hiſtorian ſaith (if my Memory fails me not) <hi>That he that writes a</hi> Lye <hi>for</hi> Truth, <hi>is the greateſt of perjured Perſons,</hi> and he gives a good Reaſon for it, becauſe he impoſeth upon Generations to come. But, I believe, your chief Reaſon for quoting this Book more than any other of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Works, except his Funeral-Sermon on the Late Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49355:7"/>
               <hi>Tillerſon,</hi> is upon the Account of the Dedication to Duke <hi>Landerdale.</hi> Now, you ſay, Sir, <hi>Not long after the printing this Book at</hi> Glaſgow, (this is true that this Book was printed at Glaſgow, and that in the Year 1673 and that it was dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Duke of <hi>Landerdale,</hi> then High Commiſſioner of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) that the Dedication is in ſubſtance what you have printed, though not printed exactly word for word: For in your firſt Paragraph you ſay that he tells the <hi>Duke,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>How wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily he bore that Noble Character, with the more laſting and noble Characters</hi> of a Princely Mind,</q> in the Dedication it is <hi>inward Character,</hi> and ſo likewiſe you ſay, <hi>and praiſes him for the long uninterrupted Tranquility that Kingdom had enjoyed under his wiſe and happy Conduct;</hi> whereas in the Dedication it is, <hi>and under whoſe wiſe and happy Conduct, we have enjoyned ſo long a <hi>Tract</hi> of uninterrupted Tranquility.</hi> This, I now ſay, I find true by the ſaid Book, which I have now in my Hand at the writing of this Paſſage; but what have I to do with the <hi>Dedication,</hi> as to the difference of the Expreſſions? Let the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> look to that, he being moſt immediately concerned. I go on; then you ſay, <q>
                  <hi>He</hi> (that is, you mean as I take it, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) <hi>brought a great part of the Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to</hi> London,</q> 
               <hi>where he ſold it to Mr.</hi> Moſes Pitt. Indeed, Sir, if you remember this Paſſage ſo well you have a good Memory, and you muſt have been a very familiar Acquaintance of mine, at that time, that you ſhould know my Tranſactions and Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; for indeed I do not remember that the Preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Dr <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> did bring a great part of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his ſaid Book, Entituled, <hi>A Vindication of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>London.</hi> Neither do I remember he ſold it, as you ſay, to me <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> that I had ſome of them, I believe, but of whom I do not at this great diſtance of Time remember; and therefore in this particular muſt refer my ſelf to Mr. <hi>Angus,</hi> who tells me that I had them from ſome Bookſeller out of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in Barter for ſome other Books, and then you go on and ſay; <hi>And not long after that again, He</hi> (I preſume you mean, the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) <hi>came to him</hi> (that is, as I underſtand it, to me <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi>) <hi>to deſire him with great earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſell the Copies of it without the Dedication.</hi> Sir, I aſſure you, I do not remember any thing of this Paragraph, but do believe the contrary, that the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> did ever
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49355:7"/>come to me to deſire me with great Earneſtneſs, or otherwiſe to ſell the Copies of it without the Dedication; neither do I remember I ever ſold one Copy without the Dedication to any Perſon whatſoever, as to what you ſay: <q>
                  <hi>For by this time the Duke had fallen out with him, and diſcarded him for ſome Arts and Qualities he had obſerved in him.</hi>
               </q> Indeed, Sir, I have heard, that as you and others might likewiſe hear, that the <hi>Duke</hi> and the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> did fall out, but what the Ground of their Quarrel was, I was not privy to, neither can I tell for what <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Qualities</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> diſcarded him; he can, I preſume if he he pleaſes, give you the beſt Account of this Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, and therefore to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> I leave it, and proceed. You ſay, <q>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Pitt <hi>gave him very good Reaſons why he ought not to do ſo; and particularly told him he could not honeſtly ſell an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect for a perfect Copy:</hi>
               </q> Sir, if this Story of yours had been true, I ſhould have (I hope) acted the honeſt Part, as you here relate; but, Sir, though my Oppreſſions on me have been, and are great, by reaſon of falſe Oaths, by which I have loſt my Eſtate of about 1500 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> &amp;c. (an Account of which you will find in my Book, called, <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed</hi>) and have been a Priſoner ever ſince the <hi>18th.</hi> Day of <hi>April</hi> 1689. which was but a Week after King <hi>William</hi> and his late Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was Crowned, and have Multitudes of Enemies upon the Account of contending againſt my own Oppreſſors, and the Oppreſſors of the Creditors of <hi>Benjamin Hinton,</hi> late of <hi>London,</hi> Goldſmith, Banker and Bankrupt; there being now at this time a Bill of 349 Sheets pending in Chancery againſt fifty Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, for the Diſcovery of the ſaid Bankrupt's Eſtate, which is unjuſtly kept from the Creditors, which I hope will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and as we have laid it in our Bill, to the Value of One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pound, or ſome ſuch great Summ: And now, Sir, I have cauſe to ſuſpect, that by reaſon of decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Truth</hi> in this Matter, as you your ſelf own, I can <hi>teſtifie if living,</hi> I ſhall raiſe to my ſelf Legions of Enemies; however, <hi>Truth</hi> I will own, ſeeing you have called me ſo fairly to it, and if you and your Party be diſobliged, I will ſay in my Dear Lord and Saviour's Words, whom I will imitate and follow ſo far as He is to be imitated by poor Mortals: <hi>Am I your Enemy becauſe I tell you the Truth?</hi> It's <hi>Truth,</hi> you have given me a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair Character, with which a great many Men in the World
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49355:8"/>would have pleaſed themſelves with, and parted with <hi>Truth,</hi> and not declar'd it; and liv'd and hug'd themſelves with the vain Conceit of the World's believing them <hi>honeſt Men,</hi> and that they had a <hi>good Name</hi> in the World, but I, for my own part, muſt part with that Character of a <hi>good Name,</hi> though it be <hi>better than precious Ointment,</hi> when it ſtands in competition with <hi>Truth,</hi> and therefore I muſt undeceive you and the World; I do not remember, neither do I believe, that there ever was any ſuch Paſſage as you have related, or that I ever gave the <hi>Biſhop</hi> any ſuch good Reaſon, you mention, and ſo <hi>farewel a good Name,</hi> when it ſtands in competition with <hi>Truth.</hi> And then you go on and ſay, <q>
                  <hi>Upon which <hi>He</hi>
                  </hi> (I ſuppoſe you ſtill mean the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) was <hi>angry, and threatned <hi>Him</hi>
                  </hi> (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you mean, my ſelf, <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi>) <hi>with the Loſs of all the Favours he intended to do him in his Trade.</hi>
               </q> This, Sir, is ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harſh an Expreſſion, that it's not to be ſuppoſed I could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it, if the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> had ſaid it, to my dying Day; but I declare I do not remember, neither do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he, the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> ever ſaid it, or any thing like it. Then you ſay, "<hi>This Mr.</hi> Pitt <hi>can teſtifie, if he is living;</hi> I hope you are now fully ſatisfied I am living; and who knows but the Great and Good God has preſerved my Life, and the Life of Mr. <hi>Angus</hi> alſo hitherto to glorifie his Name, in declaring and teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Truth</hi> in this particular Matter. Indeed, Sir, I own a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a living Grave, and he that by Charity takes a Man out of Priſon, does a Work next to raiſing the dead (ſome Account of this ſhall be given of one of thoſe great Men, you mention in your Book, towards the latter End of this my Letter.) As for my being in the Land of the Living it had been no hard Task for you to have ſatisfied your ſelf, either by your Bookſeller or Printer, or both; for I preſume that moſt (I was going to ſay almoſt all, but I conſider before whom I ſpeak) of the Maſter-Bookſellers and Printers in <hi>London,</hi> perſonally know me, or have heard of me, and the Oppreſſions I am under, ſo that they could ſoon have ſatisfied you I was living wh n you penn'd this Paſſage. <q>
                  <hi>But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>if he is not, it can be atteſted by an honourable Perſon, who heard him ſolicite Mr.</hi> Pitt <hi>to this baſe and unworthy practice.</hi>
               </q> It's <hi>True,</hi> it had been a baſe unworthy Practice of the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (I believe he himſelf would own it) provided it had been <hi>Truth.</hi> But, Sir, I wiſh you had nam'd whoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49355:8"/>this Honourable Perſon is that can atteſt this, that he heard the Biſhop ſolicite me, whether of the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s, or of your own, or of <hi>Mine,</hi> or of all, or either of us, and when it was and where it was: And if he can put it into my remembrance, by naming Tokens, and Circumſtances, or any way whatſoever whereby I may call it to my Memory, and remember the thing ſo as to atteſt it, I will aſſure you, Sir, I will obſerve what my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> directs in this Caſe, in his Moral Eſſays; <hi>Alway turn to the Pole of Truth;</hi> ſo that, if this you write of the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s be a <hi>Truth,</hi> and I be fully in my Conſcience convinced of it, as I am now convinc'd it is falſe. I will then <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, Repent, Confeſs,</hi> and <hi>Publiſh</hi> to the <hi>World</hi> my great <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>beg Pardon</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>You</hi> for it. But, Sir, I have often been thinking who this <hi>Honourable Perſon</hi> ſhould be that can atteſt this; it cannot be the late Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> who was that worthy (I want proper words to expreſs my ſelf) Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that brought my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and me firſt acquainted, and recommended me to print for him, and we have been in Converſation together, but he is dead, ſo he cannot be the Perſon; (Sir, I wiſh we had this great Man, (I mean) <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Boyle</hi>'s Life wrote fully by a good Pen, and though it were by the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (whom you ſo much deſpiſe) it would be very acceptable to the Great and Learned Men of the World;) Sir, I cannot think but of one <hi>Honourable Perſon</hi> more, that I had at that time the Honour of a familiar Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with, but I think it not proper for me at this time to name him; but if I ſhould, I ſhould do it with as much Reſpect, and make him (in my opinion) as great a Heroe as the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> has made the late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> as you have expreſt it in your Preface; for indeed he is the <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> unto whom I do own I had the beſt of my Knowledge in Authours of Books, and the Subjects they wrote on, he being a Man of gentile and univerſal Learning, but I forbear to ſpeak his due Commendations, leſt you and the World ſhould think I flatter him; but I will aſſure you, that I do not remember that ever the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and him, and my ſelf, were ever in Converſation together; but I do own that the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Edw. Stillingfleet</hi> with this Perſon of Honour and my ſelf have been in Converſation together, and this <hi>Perſon of Honour</hi> was the Spoakſman, and I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49355:9"/>have reaſon to believe that his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> had then a great Honour and Reſpect for him, and did value him as one of his chiefeſt Acquaintance, and did preſent him with one of his Books, ſoon after they were printed; and I have ſeveral times in King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>'s Reign met with this Honourable Perſon, paſſant in the Street, and we ſaluted each other after a friendly Manner, and therefore he could not be ignorant of my being in the Land of the Living: And then, Sir, you go on and tell the World; <q>
                  <hi>But though Mr</hi> Pitt <hi>would not conſent to ſell the Books without the Dedication, yet he was content to let him have them again, and then they came abroad without it.</hi>
               </q> Sir, as to this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph I do not believe, neither do I remember that ever I did conſent to the Sale of one of the Books without the Dedication, neither do I believe or remember that ever I was content to let him have them again, or that he ever had them again from me, or that ever they came abroad without it. And then you tell the World again; <q>
                  <hi>And ſo hard it was till it was privately Reprinted to get one ſingle Copy with it, that I profeſs I could never get ſuch a one, till a Gentleman preſented me with one out of his private Study.</hi>
               </q> As to the private Reprinting of the ſaid Dedication I know nothing of it; and as to your not being able to get one ſingle Copy with it, I know nothing of; but I believe if you had come to me for it, I ſhould have been able, and very willing, then to have furniſhed you with one. But as to your being preſented with one by a Gentleman out of his private Study, I know nothing of this. Then you go on and ſay; <q>
                  <hi>And when he delated his Patron to the Houſe of Commons, Sir,</hi> A. Forreſter, <hi>his Grace's Secretary, told me, That after the utmoſt Diligence, he could get but on ſingle Copy with the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though he would have purchaſed more at any Rate, to ſhew the Geutlemen of the Honourable Houſe, what kind of Man his Evidencer was, that would publiſh ſuch things in the Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Duke after he knew</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(a) See his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication in his <hi>xviij</hi> Papers.</note> 
                  <hi>as he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he had a Deſign of bringing in an Army out of</hi> Scotland, <hi>for the ſpoiling and ſubduing of</hi> England.</q> As for Sir <hi>Andrew Forreſter,</hi> I knew him, and if he had applied himſelf to me, I believe I could have ſold him what he had a mind to buy: As for the Cauſe or Ground of the Quarrel between the Duke and the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> I knew not till you had printed it in this your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49355:9"/>Book, neither am I any way concern'd in it. The preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> has moſt reaſon to know this Matter of Fact beſt, and therefore I leave it to him to declare the Truth of it to the World, it being his proper Province: Then you go on and tell the World. <q>This Diſcovery of the Dedication, and his ſuppreſſing of it, coming to be known, made all the Houſe curious to ſee it: And he foreſeeing what uſe would be made of it againſt him, was willing to decline his Noble Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: But the Houſe by the Intereſt of the Duke's Friends, who increaſed much upon that Diſcovery, made him teſtifie what he ſince ſaith, <hi>created Horrour</hi> in him; and how much Reputation he got by it I need not now tell the World. I am ſure many of the Duke's greateſt Enemies looked upon it as an horrible Lye; not thinking the Deſign, or the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it, if he had deſigned it, conſiſtent with ſo much Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as he was Maſter of, above moſt great Men of his time.</q> Really, Sir, as to the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Dedication to the <hi>Duke,</hi> I do not know nor remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber any thing at all of it, nor of all the Houſe (I preſume you mean the Houſe of Commons) curious to ſee it; and then you go on and ſay: <q>And how much Reputation he got by it, I need not now tell the World Neither,</q> Sir, have I need, now, to tell the World what Reputation you have got by printing this Story on the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and appealing to me to atteſt, but leave the World to judge. Then, as for your ſaying I am ſure (did you at that time call to mind you were giving your Depoſition in this Matter, and that in Print, which is the moſt publick Record?) <q>Many of the Duke's greateſt Enemies looked upon it as an horrible Lye;</q> Theſe words <hi>horrible Lye,</hi> is ſuch a harſh Expreſſion, that its being ſaid off-hand, and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, has coſt many a Man's Life; and if it has been of ſo miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Conſequence, when ſpoken in Heat, and Paſſion; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes it might be juſtly, and truly ſaid, and that without <hi>Scandalum Magnatum;</hi> How much more provoking is it, when it's not only ſpoken, but printed, and that againſt a now Peer of the Land? which cannot be ſuppoſed to be done in Heat and Paſſion, (as you your ſelf plainly declare in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to your ſaid Book) but all the World muſt judge it muſt be done falſly, injuriouſly, and out of pure Malice, contrary to your own Declaration in the ſaid Preface. I will aſſure you, Sir, I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49355:10"/>do not ſay this to provoke the <hi>Biſhop</hi> any way to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on you (far be it from me;) but on the contrary, if I could have the Honour of adviſing his Lordſhip, I would give him the ſame Advice I would take my ſelf, by revenging my ſelf by a frank, free, and hearty Forgiveneſs of you; for both he and you, and I muſt know who hath ſaid, <hi>Vengeance is mine and I will repay;</hi> it's the Great and True <hi>God</hi> Himſelf that ſaid it: And further Our Dear <hi>Lord and Saviour</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are you when Men revile you and perſecute you, and ſpeak all Manner of Evil againſt you falſly for my Name's ſake, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you:</hi> And ſhall the <hi>Biſhop</hi> then be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry he is thus perſecuted? I will aſſure you, Sir, if this were my Caſe as it's the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s, I would obſerve Our Dear <hi>Lord and Saviour</hi>'s Direction, to <hi>rejoyce and be glad, for great is their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven that are ſo reviled,</hi> and he has alſo told us, that <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful for they ſhall obtain Mercy,</hi> theſe are words of Truth, and <hi>by our words we ſhall be juſtified, and by our words ſhall we be condemned.</hi> But it's not my Province to preach to the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> neither I preſume, Sir, to you, I only further tell you, I my ſelf have been ſcandalized even to the Danger of my Life, (vide, <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed,</hi> page 125.) and I do confeſs, I did ſue my Adverſary in an <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Scandal,</hi> and had Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges given me (as is in that Book related) but I will aſſure you, Sir, I did not do it out of any way of Revenge for the Injuries he has done me, (as related in that Book) but only purely to vindicate my Reputation, which is as dear, if not dearer, to me than my Life; he having then at that time newly thrown me into Priſon: And having now this fair Opportunity, I do as in the Preſence of <hi>God, Angels,</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> declare, That I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to forgive my Oppreſſors as to Injuries done my ſelf, by impriſoning my Body for almoſt ſeven Years, and robbing me of my Eſtate, by falſe Oaths, and all other perſonal Injuries whatſoever. As the Great, True, and Merciful <hi>God</hi> forgives all Sinners (that is) upon their true Repentance, Confeſſion, and Reſtitution as far as they are able; which are the ſame Terms I my ſelf deſire forgiveneſs from <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> wherein I have offende. But for their <hi>Blaſphemies, Perjuries,</hi> and other Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Sins, wherein the Honour of our True <hi>God</hi> is concern'd, it's not my Province to pardon, and if they are at any Time hereafter proſecuted for it, it ſhall not be in Revenge, but purely
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49355:10"/>that <hi>Juſtice may run down our Streets like Streams, and Rihteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs like mighty Rivers,</hi> and that the Honour of our True <hi>God</hi> may be vindicated to the Terror of the Wicked, and Rejoycing of the Righteous.</p>
            <p>And although you ſo much deſpiſe the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and tell the World how apt he is to write <hi>Lives:</hi> I will give it you in your own VVords, as in Page the <hi>10th.</hi> of your Preface, you ſay: <q>And when I conſider how apt he is to write Lives, and to write his own Imaginations and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in them, I could not but bewail the Fate of the late Honourable Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> after that of Biſhop <hi>Bedel;</hi> ſhould he alſo write his Life, as Report ſaith he deſigns to do. And I cannot but wiſh, for the Honour of that great Man's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, that his Honourable Relations would oblige ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of unblemiſhed Reputation to write it, whom the World hath no reaſon to ſuſpect,</q> even when he writes <hi>Truth.</hi> Sir, As to this Point of writing of the late Honourable Mr. <hi>Robert Boyle</hi>'s Life, I will give you the following Account. Some time before I knew or heard of the publiſhing your Book, I met (as I was paſſing through the <hi>Temple</hi>) with Mr. <hi>John Warr,</hi> who was Steward to Mr. <hi>Robert Boyle</hi> many Years, and ſo continued to Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Death, and Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> had that Eſteem for him, that he made him one of his Executors in his laſt Will; after ſome Diſcourſe we had about Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s putting 500 <hi>l.</hi> into <hi>Benj. Hinton</hi>'s Hands, which is a Loſs to his Eſtate to this Day. I ask'd Mr. <hi>Warr</hi> what was the reaſon Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Life was not all this time publiſhed to the World, he gave me this for Anſwer; That the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and others, (I think he ſaid, and <hi>others,</hi> but I am not certain, I would keep to <hi>Truth</hi> as near as in words I could,) had deſired him to get Materials ready for that Work, but he ſaid the Labour was ſo great, and his Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of Reward not conſiderable, and alſo he having Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own on his Hands, that he could not well ſpare his Time for to do it, and then alſo the Fatigue would be great, for that to do it well, he muſt look over Hundreds of Books, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and Letters, which he could not well ſpare Time to do; this was his Excuſe to me, that Mr. <hi>Boyl</hi>'s Life was not to this Day publiſhed to the VVorld. Now, Sir, do you not think, but if the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> had publiſhed the Life of Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> it would not have been very acceptable to the World; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49355:11"/>he having made uſe of Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Steward for ſo many Years, to ſearch Books, Papers, and Letters, which are in the Nature of Records in this Affair of writing Lives; and who can be preſumed to know Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s private Tranſactions better than him; and Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> himſelf demonſtrated the Eſteem he had for him, by making him one of his Executors, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the VVorld could not blame the Biſhop for uſing of him, and truſting to him in this Affair, of bringing him Materials for ſo good a VVork; and I doubt not, but the Biſhop would have very Honourably rewarded Mr. <hi>Warr,</hi> for his great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue in this Affair. For I hear a very great Character of the Biſhop's Generoſity, and alſo Charity, from one I preſume ſhould know, as well as any whatever. I will give it you in his own VVords to me; That the Biſhop is <hi>No covetous Man, no lover of Money,</hi> for, ſaid he, <hi>if the Biſhop had</hi> 20000 <hi>l.</hi> per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>he would diſpoſe of it, and give it away honourably, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably.</hi> I do not write this to flatter his Lordſhip, for I abhor and ſcorn Flattery, for I never had any other Advantage or Benefit from the Biſhop, than what I have had in way of Trade, and the ſame for ought I know, I might have had from you; for I have reaſon to believe you have been a familiar Acquaintance of mine, by your Quotation. And,</p>
            <p>Sir, I am of the Opinion, that when any Man, eſpecially a Peer of the Realm, is ſcandalized in his Reputation, it behoves all Men to vidicate them and their Reputation, ſo far as <hi>Truth</hi> is on their Side: Although, I am alſo of your Opinion, that if any Man, much more great Men do ill and baſe Actions, they ought to be told of it, and that publickly; for it's no Fault in the Relator, but the Fault is his that did the ill Action. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I was at a Coffee-Houſe (and I think it was before this laſt Revolution) where I heard that moſt Learned Mr <hi>Dodwel,</hi> who indeed is a great Example of Heroick Piety and Vertue, as you your ſelf own, in the 53 Page of your Book, tell a Learned Knight, well known in this Nation. (I name him not, becauſe I would not give Offence to any Man, or Party of Men) in expreſs words; that he was a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> the Knight anſwered Mr. <hi>Dodwel,</hi> I am no <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dodwel</hi> replies, Sir, I will not believe you; the Knight anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, Sir, I am a Gentleman; why, will you not believe me on my Word; no, Sir, ſaith Mr. <hi>Dodwel,</hi> I will not believe your
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49355:11"/>Words, but I will believe your VVritings; for your Books denotes you a <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi> So, I ſay, it's not your Sayings, no, nor VVritings, that can make the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> an ill Man, but it muſt be his own VVritings, and VVorks, that muſt make him an ill or a good Man, let his Lordſhip look to that, I have told Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, and leave it to the VVorld to judge between the Biſhop and your Self, it's You, and not the Biſhop, has called on me to write what I have written, and it's <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I am upon this great Subject of writing Lives; let me alſo give my Opinion, which is, that if the Lives of great and good Men were wrote by their moſt intimate Friends, that were Perſons of <hi>Unblemiſhed Reputation,</hi> that would not write their own Fancies and Inventions for <hi>Truth,</hi> but would take on them the Fatigue of ſearching of Books, Papers, and Letters, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Perſon, whoſe Life they intend to write, and report Matters of Fact faithfully, it would be a very uſeful and acceptable Work; for Examples of Heroick Piety and Vertue, are more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and prevalent with Mankind, than juſt Precepts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. And although it be a Truth, Sir, you aſſert in the 72 Page of your Book, that our <hi>Hookers, Sanderſons,</hi> and <hi>Hamomnds,</hi> &amp;c. have aſſerted the great Truths of Religion, as zealouſly as his Heroe did; but, Sir, what need of theſe Compariſons, and that in ſo much heat; had we not alſo the <hi>Uſhers,</hi> the <hi>Pearſons,</hi> which have done the like? And we have the four firſt of theſe great and good Men's Lives written, and we are beholding to the Writers of them; and why ſhould we not alſo covet the Lives of the <hi>Pearſons,</hi> the <hi>Wilkins,</hi> and the <hi>Tillotſons,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo the great Aſſertors of the great Truths of the Chriſtian Religion? its not to be doubted but their Lives would be very acceptable to all good Men, but eſpecially to the Clergy, that ſo they might imitate their Heroick Piety and Vertue? Do you not think, Sir, but the Lives of our <hi>Cooks, Crooks,</hi> and <hi>Rolles</hi> would not be very uſeful and acceptable to our Lawyers, and alſo the Lives of our <hi>Harveys, Willis,</hi> and <hi>Lowers</hi> to our Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and our <hi>Bacons, Hales,</hi> and <hi>Boyles</hi> to our Philoſophers? (I appeal how acceptable the Life of Sir <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by our preſent Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> has been to this Nation) I muſt beg the Biſhop's Pardon for inſerting one Expreſſion here of that good Man Sir <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi> which I believe he has not in his Life (I have living Authority for it unto whom he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49355:12"/>ſaid it) That when he publiſhed the Life of <hi>Pomponius Atticus,</hi> he did ſuſpect that the World would believe, that he therein wrote his own.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I cannot forbear telling you what I lately Read (as I remember) in <hi>Diogenes Laertius,</hi> who giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Life of one of his Philoſophers, That as for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy he had no Eſteem of, and altogether neglected it; but he was ſo intent on, and ſtudious of moral Philoſophy, that he did not allow himſelf time to comb his Head, nor pair his Nails.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am of opinion, that either of our three great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, were as eminent for moral Philoſophy, as <hi>Diogenes Laer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his Philoſopher ever was, as is evident by my Lord <hi>Bacons</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays, Moral and Divine, my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hale's Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, Divine and Moral,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Boyle's Occaſional Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. yet they were not ſuch Slovens as to neglect combing their Heads, or pairing their Nails; neither were they ſuch Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks as to neglect Natural, no nor Experimental Philoſophy, as their Learned Works publiſhed to the World demonſtrate: Thus I end this Subject.</p>
            <p>As for the late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>John Tillotjon,</hi> you have not called me to give my Teſtimony of him, therefore I leave it to his Learned and Pious VVorks, which are already publiſhed to the VVorld, and alſo to his intimate Friends to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate him, which I believe they will readily do.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, I hope you will pardon me for telling you now and then a <hi>Truth,</hi> which is to the Purpoſe, and the Matter we are ſpeaking of; when I firſt came to live at my Houſe in <hi>Dukeſtreet Weſtminſter,</hi> I was ſeveral times robb'd, at laſt I diſcovered the Felon, whoſe Name was <hi>Benſon,</hi> he was one of my Laborers; he had not only ſtolen Lead, but had alſo got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into my Houſe (which was the ſame Houſe I afterwards let to the then Lord Chancellor <hi>Jefferies</hi>) and when he was in, he broke the Handle of a Pick-Ax, by his endeavouring to break open one of the Inner-doors, but could not, which Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Pick-Ax we found the next Morning; but he opened a Trunk or Trunks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſtole Cloaths, Linnen, and Plate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ſoon as I diſcovered him, he fled for it; but ſome days after he was taken by ſome of my Workmen, and brought to me; as ſoon as he ſaw me he fell on his Knees, and confeſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49355:12"/>Fact and his Confederate; and begging me pardon, Multitudes of People being by, as it's uſual upon ſuch Occaſions, urged me to ſend for a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> and carry him before a <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Pcace,</hi> that ſo he might be ſent to <hi>Goal;</hi> I told the People I would not do that, for if I did he might be hanged, and I would not have my Hand in the Blood of any Man (except for Murther,) for it was my Opinion, that nothing but Blood did require Blood; and therefore ſaid I, <hi>Benſon,</hi> I freely forgive thee, but take care be never guilty more of the like Crimes, leſt thou ſhouldeſt not fall into the Hands of ſo merciful a Man as I am: Not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, for ſome other Crime he was hanged out of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial-Sea-Priſon</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi> This Story I do not tell any way to reflect on you, but for Caution to ſome that read this my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and alſo my own Opinion, that if a Law againſt Theſt, (as alſo Perjury and Forgery) were made correſpondent to God's own judicial Law to his People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of making ſour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Reſtitution; it would be a greater Terror to this ſort of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable People, than hanging or ſtanding in the Pillory. I have many Arguments to prove this my Aſſertion, but I forbear and leave it to our <hi>Parliament,</hi> now aſſembling. Sir, I would have you weigh and conſider that Place of Scripture you quote in the 45 Page of your own Book, it's 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ſay: <hi>But the Houſe, by the Intereſt of the Duke's Friends who increaſed much upon that Diſcovery.</hi> In Anſwer to this I muſt tell you, good Men are apt to be miſtaken, and wicked Men are given up to believe Lyes, for the <hi>Truth</hi> of which, I could, beſides the Inſtances mentioned in Scripture, tell you of ſome Modern Examples to this purpoſe; the Conſequences of which have been very miſchievous. I could mention a Paſſage which I can prove by living Witneſſes of a National Concern; but I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear till it's proper Seaſon. And further you go on and ſay, "made him teſtifie what he ſince ſaith, <hi>created Horrour</hi> in him. What <hi>Horrour</hi> this Created in the <hi>Biſhop</hi> he can beſt tell; but I will aſſure you, Sir, if this Caſe had been mine, I ſhould father have rejoyced, by reaſon the Story of ſuppreſſing the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was falfe, ſo far as I know, believe, or can remember.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, I have given you my Teſtimony as to this Paſſage in your Book, which concerns the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Dedication to his Book, call'd, his <hi>Vindication of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Laws of Scotland.</hi> And I have done it with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49355:13"/>Integrity and Simplicity, and as near to <hi>Truth</hi> as in Words I could expreſs it. And this I have done, as I believe I muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it before our Great <hi>God,</hi> who is a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and knows the Hearts, not only of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>my Self,</hi> but of all Men.</p>
            <p>As for all other Paſſages in your Book, I have nothing to ſay to them, I leave them to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> who is of Age, and very well able to anſwer for himſelf. And now, Sir, give me leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude this my Letter, to tell you ſomething of the now Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> I tell it you on my own Knowledge, and I have alſo other living Witneſſes to prove it. And I farther declare, I publiſh it without his or any of his Friends approbation or knowledge; and when he did this great Work of Charity, he then obliged me to ſecrecy; as to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had the Benefit of it, and therefore I ſhall not now name him by that Denomination you have given him, in the 2<hi>d.</hi> Pag. of your Preface, I will give it you in your own words, which are, <hi>The Remarks on the late Funeral-Sermons,</hi> &amp;c. <q>
                  <hi>The Letter to the Authour of the Funeral-Sermon at</hi> VVeſtminſter-<hi>Abby: Theſe Diſcourſes,</hi> not to mention others long ſince Printed, will let Poſterity ſee what kind of Man our <hi>Preacher,</hi> and his <hi>Heroe,</hi> and his <hi>Heroe's Succeſſor,</hi> not to mention others; and what pernicious Doctrines were vented by them all,</q> (as for theſe pernicious Doctrines vented by them all, I have nothing to ſay, I leave to them to juſtifie what they have both ſaid and publiſhed) <q>and ſo help to convert the Lovers of <hi>Truth,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Libels</hi> in former Times converted many, and helped to bring the Nation to its Wits, and the exiled King back to his Throne.</q> By <hi>The Remarks on the late Funeral-Sermons,</hi> &amp;c. you mean the Sermon of the preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> on the late Lord <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> and the preſent Lord <hi>Archbiſhop</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on our late <hi>Queen,</hi> whoſe <hi>Grace</hi> you are pleaſed to term our <hi>Preacher's Heroe's Succeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I am of opinion that when any Man, much more when the firſt Peer of the Nation is ſcandalized, every one that can, ought to clear his Reputation to the World, and that is the true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I tell the World what <hi>Charity-Moneys</hi> he has put into my Hands, and the good Effects it has wrought (I have heard and believe, that his Charity to others alſo has been very large and extenſive, but I report no more than I know) ſo that the World
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49355:13"/>may ſee, how the beſt of Men are often moſt ſcandalized. I received from his Grace, <hi>Nov.</hi> 21. 1691. 21 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> and on the <hi>4th,</hi> of <hi>January</hi> following 20 <hi>l.</hi> more, which makes 41 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> I believe I had more Moneys of him, but I cannot now call the particulars to remembrance. With this Charity-moneys I releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (beſides what I relieved) out of the <hi>Marſhal-Sea-Priſon,</hi> and the Common ſide of the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Bench,</hi> near about 20 Priſoners, as can be teſtified by Mr. <hi>Francis Beale,</hi> now of the <hi>Marſhall-Sea,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sam. Malcher</hi> then Turn-key of the Common-ſide of the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Bench;</hi> beſides, I took out of the Counter in <hi>Southwark,</hi> one <hi>John Miller,</hi> who had a Wife and two or three ſmall Children, he was in Execution for 100 <hi>l.</hi> and I agreed with his Adverſary for 6 <hi>d.</hi> in the Pound, and paid his Priſon-Fees; and I alſo got one Mr. <hi>Lewis Owen</hi> a Counſellor of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colns-Inn,</hi> who had a Wife and ſeveral Children, (who was in Priſon (as he told me) for 6000 <hi>l.</hi>) out of the ſaid Priſon, with the help of 20<hi>s.</hi> which his Wife had gotten. But the greateſt and moſt notable Effect of this Charity-moneys was this, which I now relate following; In <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi>-Holy Days, 1691. I was with my Landlord Mr. <hi>Ben. Hinton,</hi> who broke for about 100000 <hi>l.</hi> who then had juſt newly taken the Coffee Houſe where we both lodged, then comes in two Women; one of them asked to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Hinton,</hi> he went out of the inner Coffee-Room to them; the Woman told him, Sir, we have juſt now brought a Woman to bed of a Child, and we have nothing to give her but <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Oatmeal,</hi> we beg of you, 2<hi>d.</hi> he anſwers her, I will not give you one Farthing; ſhe replies, what, Sir, will you be ſo hard hearted as not to give us, 2<hi>d.</hi> he anſwers again, he had no Charity; upon this, I hearing a Noiſe came forth to know what was the Matter: This Woman applies her ſelf to me, and tells me the Story, and how Mr. <hi>Hinton</hi> had denied her 2<hi>d.</hi> upon that I put my Hand into my Pocket, and gave her all the Moneys I had, which was 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> and 18 <hi>d.</hi> more I borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo ſhe had 5 <hi>s.</hi> of me; when ſhe was gone, I had a Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I had a Trick put on me, upon which I ask'd Mrs. <hi>Jurdane</hi> that kept the Coffee-Houſe, then as Servant to <hi>B. Hinton,</hi> if ſhe knew the Woman, who told me ſhe did, upon which her Maid went to ſee whether it were Truth of the Woman's being brought to bed, and her miſerable Condition, and ſhe brought me word it was really true, upon that, the ſame Day I begged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49355:14"/>2 <hi>s.</hi> of two Friends more, and ſent it her, by which I believe, the Life both of the Woman and Child were preſerved. (But to go on with this Story, for it has much of the Providence of God in it.) The <hi>Michaelmas Term</hi> after, Mr. <hi>Hinton</hi> deſires me to call on his Creditor who kept him in Priſon (for, ſaith he, I am in Priſon only for 100 <hi>l.</hi>) and deſire him to come over to me. I ask'd Mr. <hi>Hinton</hi> if he would pay him the 100 <hi>l.</hi> he ſaid no, he could not; then ſaid I, what ſhould I ſpeak to him for, had you not the 100 <hi>l.</hi> of him, he told me he had? At laſt I promiſed I would call on him, and I did ſo, and upon my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt his Creditor came, but he had firſt my promiſe to be there alſo, which I eaſily granted; neither would Mr. <hi>Hinton</hi> be with him without me, ſo I was the <hi>Days-man</hi> between them. When his Creditor came we three went up Stairs, where he had cauſed a Fire to be kindled, and after ſome preliminary Diſcourſe, and drinking each 2 Diſhes of Coffee, Mr. <hi>Reginald Heber</hi> (for that was his Creditor's Name) ask'd Mr. <hi>Hinton</hi> if he would pay him his 100 <hi>l.</hi> who told him he could not; then Mr. <hi>Heber</hi> replied, Mr. <hi>Hinton,</hi> notwithſtanding, you have provoked me very much, I will make you a very fair Propoſal, but I will not take your own word, for this Reaſon; becauſe you have broken it with me. But if you will give me any reaſonable Security to pay me 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Week till the Debt be out, I will let you out of Priſon; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, upon this, <hi>Ben. Hinton</hi> roſe out of his Chair, pulled off his Hatt, and put it under his Arm, with his Hands lifted up towards Heaven, appealing to the Great <hi>God</hi> that he could not pay him 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Week; upon this, I ſitting between them, roſe up and thruſt him down into his Chair, Crying out, <hi>O do not appeal to the Great God to a Lye,</hi> for your Creditor will not believe you, I will not believe you, neither will the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you; upon that, he ſaid he could not pay his Creditor 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Week; upon this, Mr. <hi>Heber</hi> and I went to Sir <hi>John Moores,</hi> ſame Propoſal, that if he would paſs his Word that <hi>B. Hinton</hi> ſhould pay him 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Week, he would go over into <hi>Southwark</hi> and let him out of Priſon immediately. Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> denied to do it, although at the time about his Breaking, <hi>B. Hinton</hi> and others have told me, that Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> profered at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to bail him as far as 100000 <hi>l.</hi> Actions, and <hi>B. Hinton</hi>'s Wiſe at the ſame time lived with Sir <hi>John</hi> as his Houſe-keeper:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49355:14"/>Then we went into <hi>Lumbardſtreet,</hi> to the Shop <hi>B. Hinton</hi> kept his Goldſmiths-Trade in, where lived <hi>Robert Hill,</hi> (who afterwards foreſwore himſelf before the Commiſſioners of the Statute of Bankrupt againſt <hi>B. Hinton,</hi> againſt two Deeds under his own Hand and Seal, which I have by me to produce on occaſion, and ſometime after died) and <hi>Francis Grevil</hi> both his Nephews, and formerly his Apprentices, Mr. <hi>Heber</hi> made Mr. <hi>Grevil</hi> the ſame profer he had made Sir <hi>John Moore,</hi> but he refuſed it, and ſaid alſo, his Partner <hi>Hill</hi> ſhould not, or would not do it neither; on <hi>Jan.</hi> 3. following, <hi>B. Hinton</hi> died; he could not die in his Bed, but lay on <hi>Jan</hi> the 2 <hi>d.</hi> and 3 <hi>d.</hi> on a Trundle-bed, juſt in the ſame place where <hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Creditor</hi> and <hi>I</hi> had the Dialogue here related, neither could he die there, till he was put into that <hi>Chair</hi> he roſe up out of, when he appealed to the Great <hi>God</hi> he could not pay 20 <hi>s. per</hi> Week, aforeſaid, and his Nurſe whoſe Name is <hi>Rebecca Trowel,</hi> that was with him when he died, and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to ſtrip him, and put him into his Coffin, was the very Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that about a twelve Month before begged 2 <hi>d.</hi> of him for the Woman that was brought to bed as afore related; and there was alſo aſſiſting to her one Mr. <hi>Richard Sandy</hi> a Barber-Chirurgeon living in <hi>Southwark,</hi> who was alſo by us when the Nurſe begged the 2 <hi>d.</hi> as aforeſaid. He had vaſt Riches by him at the time of his Death in Gold, Silver, Jewels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> although he had ſome time before ſwore himſelf not worth 10 <hi>l.</hi> for to get off by the Act for <hi>Releaſe of Priſoners;</hi> they that would be further ſatisfied in this Story, may inquire of Mr. <hi>Reginald Heber,</hi> who lives in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and may be found moſt Mornings and Evenings at the <hi>Temple-Church,</hi> at the Hours of Prayer. Now, Sir, I have told you, and the World what experience I have had of the preſent Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s Charity, for by it he has fed the Hungry, cloathed the Naked, relieved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed the Priſoners; and therefore, do you not think, Sir, <hi>that</hi> Bleſſing does not belong to him, and all ſuch charitable Perſons, which our Dear Lord and Saviour has pronounced? <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father enter into my Kingdom; for when I was an Hungry ye fed me, when I was Naked ye cloathed me, when in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you viſited me.</hi> Lord, ſay they, <hi>When ſaw we thee Hungry and fed thee, Naked, and Cloathed thee, and in Priſon, and viſited thee.</hi> In that, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>You have done it to the leaſt of my little ones, you have done it to me:</hi> And, I hope, it may be ſaid of this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49355:15"/>great and good Man, what I heard Dr. <hi>William Bates</hi> ſay of my Lord <hi>Ruſſell</hi> (they are the ſame Perſons you mention in your Book) when an Object of great Charity was repreſented to him, that my Lord gave 50 <hi>l.</hi> Dr <hi>Bates</hi> praiſing him for it, my Lord replies, Doctour, I thank God my Heart is as large as my Purſe, ſo I have found the preſent Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and I hope it will ſo continue: I would not have you think that I flatter him, far be it from me, I ſpeak nothing but what I know to be <hi>Truth;</hi> and if I knew as much of you, as I have here related of the Archbiſhop, I would publiſh it as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if I had the ſame Opportunity, as I do this.</p>
            <p>Sir, I would not have you in the leaſt think, that this good Man the preſent Archbiſhop has given his Alms, or blown a Trumpet to be ſeen, and to be praiſed of Men. No, he knows nothing of what I here write you, but if you be diſpleaſed at what I have here, by my own Experience and Knowledge; related of him, you muſt thank your ſelf for it; for if you had not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on me to atteſt what you were pleaſed to relate, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Difference between the late Duke <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and at the ſame time ſpoken ſlightly of the Archbiſhop, theſe great Acts of Charity of him had been buried in Oblivion, as to Men; but, Sir, would you have me act the part of an ungrateful Man (which is one of the worſt ſorts of Men) when I have ſo fair an Opportunity from your ſelf, to tell the World the good Works of this Charitable great Man, that ſo they may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven; and I hope, Sir, you your ſelf are of the Opinion of St. <hi>James;</hi> who tells you, <hi>That pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, to viſit the fatherleſs and widows in their affliction;</hi> And was it not <hi>Cornelius</hi>'s Praiſe, that he gave much Alms to the People, and did they not come up into remembrance before God? And does not <hi>Job,</hi> when his three Friends conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with him, glory in that he delivered the Poor that cried, and the Fatherleſs, and him that had none to help him, and cauſed the Widow's Heart to rejoyce, and that he was Eyes to the Blind, and Feet to the Lame, and was a Father unto the Poor: But I ſtop my Pen leſt I be cenſured. Sir, I have one reaſon more, why I ſo much commend this great and good Man's Charity, which is, I want Imployment (I have told you my Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) and therefore I would willingly be your, or any other
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49355:15"/>charitable Perſon's Almoner, as I have been this preſent Lord Archbiſhop's. And I will aſſure you, Sir, what Moneys I ſhall be intruſted with upon ſuch Account, ſhall be diſpoſed of with the Wiſdom of a Serpent, and the Innocency of a Dove, in feeding the Hungry, cloathing the Naked, ſupporting the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, relieving and releaſing the Impriſoned, all this ſhall be done with a chearful heart and pleaſing Countenance, my Labour and my Time ſhall alſo be given into the Bargain; this is the darling Imployment I ſhould covet whilſt I have a Being in this World; and therefore, Sir, if you, or any other charitable Perſon, will intruſt me, as the preſent Lord Archbiſhop hath already done, you, or they, ſhall hear of me at Mr. <hi>Lewis Preſcot</hi>'s Chambers, in <hi>Searle</hi>'s Court in <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> Number 4.</p>
            <p>Sir, I muſt further beg your Pardon, if I acquaint you with one Story I find related in Dr. <hi>Franklin's Annals of King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt,</hi> which is all Invention, and therefore ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, which none living, that I know, can do it better than my ſelf. It's related in the 33 <hi>d.</hi> Page of that Book, unto which I refer you (it being too large a Romance to be incerted here,) it's of a ſtrange Murther at <hi>Penrin</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Father and Mother upon their own Son, and then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves. The Truth of which (as he tells you) was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently known, and flew to Court in this guiſe; but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed Relation (which was but a Ballad) conceal their Names in favour to ſome Neighbour of Repute, and a Kin to that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and ſaith he, (the ſame ſenſe makes me ſilent alſo.) But, Sir, being one time in Converſation with one Mr. <hi>Tho. Melhuiſh,</hi> a Merchant born in that Town, and that lived there moſt of his Days, he drawing towards 80 Years of Age when he died, and left one Daughter, which is now a Baronet's Lady in that County. I ask'd him about this Story of Dr. <hi>Franklin</hi>'s, who told me, that he had before heard of it; but, ſaith he, it's all Invention; the occaſion of which was this: There was ſome Corniſh-men which were going for <hi>London,</hi> and when they drew near the City, one was ſaying to his Companions, that as ſoon as they met with their City Acquaintance, they would be asking them, what News in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and they had none to tell them; whereupon one of his Company which had a good Faculty at Invention, told them, he would ſupply that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49355:16"/>Defect, upon which he invented that Story as it is related in Dr. <hi>Franklin's Annals.</hi> Which as ſoon as they met with their Friends and Companions at the Tavern; upon their asking what News in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> he, the Romancer, told them the ſaid Story with ſo much Confidence, that it was believed by ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, who cauſed a Ballad to be made of it, and ſome few Nights after, theſe Sparks meeting at the ſame Tavern, heard the Ballad ſung in the Street juſt againſt their VVindow: From which Ballad Dr. <hi>Franklin,</hi> I ſuppoſe, had his Authority; but, Sir, as for Dr. <hi>Franklin,</hi> he was a Phyſician; and any one that reads his very firſt lines in his Book muſt imagin, he is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to read a Pomance, for he begins thus: <q>There was amongſt other Perſons of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Quality,</hi> in the Court, a young Lady of great Birth, and Beauty; <hi>Frances,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Tho. mas Howard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk;</hi> married in her Minority unto Robert</q> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> &amp;c. This is the Story of the poyſoning of Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> which has proved as fatal to a great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, As <hi>Inceſt</hi> to the Family of the <hi>Carmino</hi>'s in <hi>Cornwall;</hi> the Story is this: <hi>Carmino</hi> was reputed the ancienteſt Family we had in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> it was ſuppoſed, long before <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Days, and moſt of our Corniſh-Gentry were pleaſed, when they could derive their Pedegrees from that Family: One of the laſt of theſe <hi>Carmino</hi>'s having committed <hi>Inceſt,</hi> by lying with his own Daughter, in the Morning when he roſe, came into his Hall, and over the Chimney finds theſe words wrote:</p>
            <q>
               <l>O! <hi>Carmino,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This has bred thy Woe;</l>
               <l>This thine Iniquity</l>
               <l>Has cancell'd thine Antiquity.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Paſſage of the <hi>Carmino's,</hi> I have often heard my own Father telate, (who was born, and died in the 90<hi>th.</hi> Year of his Age, in the ſame Pariſh with <hi>Carmino</hi>) and I my ſelf knew the laſt Male-heir of the Family, who as I was informed, was in <hi>Exeter</hi> Priſon for Debt, and there died, and the Eſtate all ſpent. By this, Sir, you ſee <hi>Monſter Sins,</hi> (whereof I reckon Slandering, and taking away the Good name of our Neighbour, is one,) is the Cauſe of the Deſtruction of Perſons, Families, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. And <hi>Truth,</hi> Sir, is like the <hi>Sun,</hi> it may be <hi>Fogg'd, Cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49355:16"/>nay, <hi>Eclipſed;</hi> yet at laſt it will ſhine forth with the greater Splendour and Glory, and will diſſipate, ſcatter, and deſtroy, the <hi>Fogs, Clouds,</hi> and <hi>Eclipſes.</hi> I will perſume, Sir, you have read the 3d. and 4th. Chapters of the firſt of <hi>Eſdras;</hi> I own the Book is Apocryphal, but the laſt of the three young Men's Sentences is Canonical. The firſt wrote <hi>Wine is ſtrongeſt;</hi> the ſecond wrote <hi>the King is ſtrongeſt;</hi> and the third wrote <hi>Women are ſtrongeſt; but Truth overcometh all things.</hi> But when Judgment was to be given, and that by all the People, they cried and ſaid, <hi>Truth is great, and ſtrongeſt: And that it doth abide, and is ſtrong for ever, and liveth, and reigneth for ever, and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, no Age is ſo barren of Tragedies, that we have need to invent Romantick Murthers, (as Dr. <hi>Franklin</hi> has done in the Story related) and write them for Truths; I will parallel his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy with a more Modern one, acted in our Memory. The Paſſage is, a Major-General who was well known in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſpecially in the Weſt, in the Time of the late Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>'s Rebellion. This Perſon having the Command of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in <hi>Tangier,</hi> (before its Demoliſhment) againſt the <hi>Mocres,</hi> there was three Soldiers condemn'd by a Court-Martial; one was an Engliſh-man, the ſecond a Scotch-man, the third an Iriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. The Engliſh-man, and Scotch man, one of them was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for murthering his Comrade, the other for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urglary, and Felony, but the poor Iriſh man was condemned for ſtealing ſome Hens, which the Woman from whom they were ſtolen, had them again. All the Ladies of Quality of the Gariſon were pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners to the General, for the poor Iriſh-man's Life, but could not prevail. The General falling ſick, ſent for the Chief Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of the Gariſon, (whoſe Name is Mr. <hi>Andrew Herriot</hi>) to let him Blood; which when he had done, he fell on his Knees, and begg'd a Boon of the General; the General ask'd him what it was, he told him, he would not beg the Engliſh-man's life, nor the Scotch-man's Life, (although his Country-man) for they both deſerved to die, but he begg'd the poor Iriſh man's Life, he having ſtolen a few Hens, and the Woman from which they were ſtolen had them again: The General anſwered him, he would not grant him his Life; for he never had the Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of hanging the three Nations at one Time, nor never might have the like again, and for that Reaſon, and the Fancy of it, he ſhould be hanged; and that very Day he hanged them all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49355:17"/>three. This Relation I had from Mr. <hi>Herriot</hi>'s own Mouth, more than once: This Mr. <hi>Herriot</hi> is a Man of Veracity, and I have heard him ſpeak many a bold Truth, and I know he will juſtifie what I now write. This Story puts me in mind of the Prophet, who came to a Captain (as related in Holy Writ) and told him, he ſhould, amongſt other Villainies, rip up Women with Child. What, replies the Captain, is thy Servant a Dog? Upon which the Prophet tells him he ſhould be a King, that is, he ſhould have Power; and I muſt tell you, Sir, Power is ſuch a mighty Liquour, that it's a hard matter to get Veſſels ſtrong enough to hold it.. Sir, all I ſay on this Subject, you have done your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take away the Good name of a great Man, which is next to taking away his Life; and if I had not through mercy been in the Land of the Living to vindicate him, it would have paſſed for a Truth; (I ſpeak as to the Paſſage you call me to teſtifie, if living;) and therefore I will tell you what I would do, if I were guilty of ſuch a foul Scandal, eſpecially, it being againſt a Peer of the Realm; I would repent, and go to him, and make my Confeſſion, and beg the Great God, and him Pardon, and make him what Reſtitution was in my Power: But, Sir, I will not be ſo bold as to direct you; I preſume you are not ignorant of your Duty in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, what I have wrote you, that is of my own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is <hi>Truth,</hi> and what I have by the Information from others I believe to be <hi>Truth;</hi> and if I have offended you in words that are any ways offenſive, I beg your pardon; for, I had no ſuch deſign; and if any of thoſe Perſons whom I have ſo freely nam'd take offence at me for ſo doing, I muſt beg their Pardon; but if I muſt loſe your or their Friendſhips, for telling the <hi>Truth,</hi> then farewell Friendſhip, and Favour, and All; I ſtick to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and ſhall be yours, and all Mens, on that Account:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſes Pitt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Nov. 22.—1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed:</hi> Being a True and Tragical Account of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallell'd Sufferings of Multitudes of poor impriſoned Debtors, in moſt of the Goals in <hi>England;</hi> together with the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the Publiſher.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49355:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
